Here's an icebreaker game, an improv exercise called Enemy Defender and I love this game.
It's really good for getting people moving around the room.
It's also a great way to introduce closeness to people that might not necessarily get that close in their regular work, but in a really kind of safe playful way.
Kind of break down some of those boundaries.
So, here's how you do Enemy Defender.
I like to facilitate this game with everyone walking around the room.
So, that's the first thing I do.
I invite everybody to come down into this space.
Move around the room and just move to open space.
Kind of disperse themselves like atoms and then in the space.
They want to fill it out.
So they're just going to keep moving around.
Not just walking in a circle.
And I tell them to be very sneaky and very secretive and out of the corner of their eye, they're going to pick another person in the room.
And don't let them know you've picked them.
So, everybody is walking around the room and they're going to pick this other person and I say just keep your eye on them.
Keep it cool.
Don't let them know.
Just keep moving open space.
This person, they don't know it, but they are your enemy.
They are your secret enemy so keep your eye on them.
That usually gets a little laugh and then people keep walking and I say okay, again secretly, very sneaky, out of the corner of your eye pick a second person in the room.
So, you've got your eyes on two people.
You've got your eye on your enemy and this second person who also doesn't know it, but they are your defender.
So, everybody is walking around the room really sneaky, really subtle, keeping their eye on their enemy and defender.
And then I tell them this.
When I say go, you're going to try and keep your defender between you and your enemy.
When I say go you're going to try and keep your defender between you and your enemy.
Now, before I say go and I always say this.
Before I say go, remember safely first.
It's just a game, okay?
So, once people know they're going to be cool and be safe then I say go and everybody starts scrambling around the room because everybody's picked different people for their enemies and defenders and they're trying to position themselves in the right place and people get squished up against the wall and people are spread out and they're giggling and elbowing each other and it's super fun and I usually just let them go until people start breathing heavy or getting tired or the giggling is peaked and I say okay freeze.
Relax, with your right arm point to your enemy, bink.
With your left arm point to your defender, bop.
And everybody laughs.
Oh, you were my enemy.
You were my defender.
And it's a great icebreaker.
It's pretty fast and it gets the energy way up.
It gets people moving and gets people close together in a way that doesn't feel too creepy.
So, that's one of my favorites.
It's called enemy defender.
Oh yeah, and if you're working with kids I usually call it something like Apples and Oranges.
You don't have to use those kind of villainous terms.
That is enemy defender, an improv icebreaker.